[Music] I'm just got them one big question always for most people is all this yoga is fine
but how do I do my daily life now here we will look at how to make your daily life into yoga
how to make the simple actions that we perform into a process of Liberation into a process of
Freedom into a process of well-being rather than being a process of stress anxiety or a burden
this is important that we turn our Karma our daily activity into yoga when our very actions
that we perform become a liberating process then it is very simple and easy to manifest
to create what we care for so here is a simple understanding of how to create what you want
because if you do not create what you want within yourself to start with and then around yourself
then this is not a life that you want
a certain day
a man took a walk
as he was walking
accidentally he walked into Paradise
fortunate isn't he
just took a walk accidentally just like that an OS he walked into Paradise
he looked around and thought Oh after this long walk I feel tired
I wish I could rest somewhere he saw a nice tree
beneath the shade of the tree Nash cushy grass he went and put his head down
slept after a few hours he woke up
now I'm really well rested but I'm feeling hungry I wish I could eat something
and he thought about all the nice things that he ever wanted to eat
and all of them appeared in front of him
everything that he ever wanted to eat you know there the service is like that
hungry people don't ask questions he ate stomach became full
then he thought
ah my stomach is full I wish I had something to drink and he thought
about all the nice things he ever wanted to drink all of them appeared in front of him
drinking people also don't ask questions he drink with a little bit of alcohol in him
in yoga
foreign
what the hell is happening here
I asked for food food came
I asked for drink a drink came what the hell is happening here maybe there are ghosts around here
you've seen a ghost
that maybe their ghosts around here he looked around the ghosts were all over the place
and he said oh the ghosts have come they are going to torture me they started torturing him
he started screaming oh they're touching me they're touching me they're going to kill me
he died
just now you said he is very fortunate
but the problem was he was sitting under a culpriksha or a wishing tree
he asked for food food came he asked for a drink drink came he asked for
torture torture came he asked for death death came
even today these wishing trees are kalpa rukshas are very much present
now don't go looking for them in the forest
a well-established mind is referred to as a corporation
an unestablished mind is referred to as a marketer means a monkey why your mind is
referred to as a monkey is what are the qualities of a monkey unnecessary moment
do you do your does your mind have to learn this from the monkey or the
monkey can learn from your mind unnecessary moment
what's up the quality of a monkey
what is the other quality of a monkey if I say you are monkeying somebody what does it mean
imitation isn't it imitation is synonymous with a monkey
that's full-time job for your mic isn't it
so an unestablished mind which is in constant moment and an imitation of whatever it says
is referred to as a monkey if your mind becomes stable a state which is referred to a samyukti
now this mind is a wishing tree anything that you ask for always comes true
if anybody wants to create anything whatever man has created on this planet first he made
it happen in his mind isn't it you want to build a house first you build one in your mind
then you put it on the paper then it stands up
in your mind itself you keep demolishing every other day this is not going to stand up
but now there is a problem if let's say for example somebody is miserable
because he doesn't have his own house it's a very Indian problem
they want to live in their own house as if rented house will bite you
it doesn't bite you but somehow people think they want to live their own house
they do their own house and spend next 25 years clearing the loan
so oh I'm miserable only because I don't have my own house even the stupid neighbor he's got
his own house I don't have my own house like this they make themselves miserable
I want to build a house but to build a house
I need 50 lakhs but I have only 50 rupees not
possible on one level he's making himself miserable because he doesn't have a house
on another level he's telling himself I don't want a house when you say not possible you're
telling yourself I don't want a house isn't it now this torment goes on building and
demolishing building and demolishing within the mind is happening every day the torture goes on
someone else a very simple human being went to some Temple and said Shiva I don't know I
want my house I don't know I don't know how I have only 10 Rupees but it doesn't matter I want house
have you heard somebody went and asked and it happened for them have you any
number of people claiming like this or did Shiva come and build a house
Shiva will not lift his little pink finger for you there's a very beautiful incident
when the satta rishis you know morning I was talking to the seven sages when he told them
go and spread this in the world when they were about to leave they asked a question [Music]
they asked when we go to the strange lands if we find a position if people
torture us if people don't accept what we have to offer if we get into trouble
will you be there Shiva looked at them incredulously and said
if you find a position if you get into trouble I will sleep
he didn't say I will come and fight for you he said if you get into trouble I will sleep
if I go into this this is a very long thing why he says I will sleep because he is at his best
when he sleeps even you when you sleep you are in one with everything isn't it
you don't sleep separately do you when you sleep you sleep as part of the existence isn't it
so Shiva says if you are in trouble I will sleep that means I will merge with everything and be
there that's his way he's saying not saying I will come there and fight for you he says I will sleep
right now I'm sitting but if you get into trouble I will sleep
so Shiva will not lift his little finger for you it is just that
if you believe in something you have taken away all the negative thoughts
a thought is a reverberation a thought is a vibration
today modern science is proving to you the whole existence is a vibration
if you generate a powerful thought and let it out it always becomes a reality
but the problem with most people is they generate a thought and they kill it with hundred negative
thoughts not possible not possible how is it possible all these things what is possible what is
not possible is not your business that is Nature's business isn't it yes or no is it your business
because if you if you make it your business from what basis do you arrive at what is
possible and what is not possible I'll ask you two simple questions all of you should answer
yes no whatever is true for you from where you're sitting can you fly off right now
can you get up and run what is the basis of no and S
in the past many times you've gotten up and run so you're saying yes never before have you flown off
so you say no so what you're telling me is what has not occurred to you in your life till now will
never happen in future this is a self-defeating way of existence you are making sure nothing new
ever occurs to you in your life no new possibility ever opens up for you you are arriving at what is
possible and what is not possible only from past experience of life isn't it or in other
words your statement is very clear what has not happened till now cannot happen tomorrow
this is a disgrace to human Spirit isn't it what has not happened till now can it happen tomorrow
what has never happened till now can it happen tomorrow yes so you don't decide what is possible
and what is not possible nature will determine what is possible and what is not possible your
business is just to strive but what you care for isn't or will it happen will it not happen who
the hell cares whether it happens or not at least you're striving for what you care for
if you are doing something that you do not care for your life is already defeated isn't it
if you strive for what you care for if it happens good if it doesn't happen very good why
you can do it all over again because anywhere you care for it but if you do something that you don't
care for simply because it's going to happen before you live it your life is over isn't it
in your life if you are every day doing something that you don't care for for sure you are a
miserable human being isn't it yes or no every human being should do what he really cares for
otherwise before you live your life you already wasted it you do something because it's safe
you do something because it's easy you do something because somebody approves it you
already killed yourself before you die before you live you already kill yourself isn't it
what is it that you really care for if you look at this at every point in life
your mind is telling you this is it and tomorrow it makes you
feel like a fool for what you thought yesterday has it happened to you many times
at every point in your life you thought this is it if I do this this is it but you do it
and you feel like a fool after some time because that's not it something else is it
if you do not even know what you really care for
the question of creating it doesn't Arise at all what is it that you really care for
I want you to remove this what is possible and not possible out of your head just if you had
an opportunity right now to become the ideal kind of human being that you want to become
your ideal passion that your ideal image of yourself if you could become
what kind of human being would you want to become
and if you could have an ideal world right now right now if you can have an Ideal World
do not think in terms of what's possible not possible what is it that you want in this world
what kind of a world do you want to live in what kind of a human being do you want to be
yeah
say it said it's a
for the last part I didn't get that
as much
I mean as much as I can for Rural education like endlessly why do you want to do rural education
suppose I don't want to get educated I don't want to get educated you want to educate me
also no but I think it is a great need over there for Education what is it that you really want
okay plural education happens after that what
suppose rural people don't want to be educated they're happy what's your problem
no don't they need to eat they need to earn money they need to put bread on the table so
for that they need to be educated they are the people who are making the bread not you
but that's it doesn't take money to have bread you just you just have to plow and plant to have bread
isn't it but that's also depleting the farmers income is depleting over the years you know you
you're getting lost in this now what is it that you really want why you want them to have bread
you want them to be happy yeah I oh you want a happy world why don't you say that
why are you going rural education then bread then happiness then this
suppose without eating I'm happy what's your problem
no bread I am happy what is your problem this is
Lex you know don't fix it how somebody should be
happy isn't it everybody must be educated like you why I don't want to be educated I'm happy is
it okay with you is it okay with you I don't want to eat I fast and I'm happy is it okay with you
so don't fix how they should be happy you want
yourself to be happy you want the world to be happy she wants a happy world what do you want
you want a happy world
see this is the biggest problem with Humanity what Petty thinks they'll stand up and fight
for things that really matter they will never even utter they'll never even express how
many of you at least in your own home for this few people in your home have clearly
expressed I want to live in a joyful home you won't say small things you will fight
but real things that neither we will not utter
I am asking you do you want a happy world
that's not enough do you want a happy world what else do you want
um
what that's enough okay happy world what else you said something okay um for men to respect
nature and nature to be preserved why because we are taking up all the space and the wildlife is
suffering and we are just encroaching on this space and we're abusing just about everything
no no no why do you want this so that other living beings also have a chance to you
want a happy world yes yes happy worms happy and sex Happy Birds happy people
happy elephants that's what you want we already saw that what else do you want
peaceful and United you want a peaceful world he wants a peaceful world do you want a peaceful word
you want a peaceful world what else do you want the whole world to get enlightened
why suppose somebody who doesn't want to get enlightened why do you want to light them up
I want my own happiness I'm sorry my own happiness and we said happy world it includes you also man
you want yourself to be happy and the world to be happy yourself to be peaceful in the world
to be peaceful what kind of relationships do you want to hold [Music] to do whatever I want
we said a happy world happy world means everybody is doing whatever the hell they want
yes necessarily not necessarily whatever I do may not make you happy no no it's not a question of
what you do should make me happy all I'm saying is when we say a happy word somebody wants to do
this somebody wants to do that somebody wants to do nothing it's left to them isn't it you
want to do whatever I want to do because you think that is your happiness isn't it I'm sorry
that will create a conflict of interest because my happiness will be someone else's misfortune
your happiness is never somebody's
Misfortune it is just that
we are always thinking only if I do this I will be happy yes if you are happy you will be a very
flexible human being and everybody will have enough space to do whatever the hell they want
don't don't get into the details of it I'm just asking fundamentally what you want
you want a peaceful world you want a happy world what kind of relationships do you want to hold you
want a loving world you want a loving world she wants a loving world do you want a loving world
seven people
so you're peaceful the world is peaceful you're joyful the world
is joyful you are loving the world is loving is that what you want
now you can go into details I want a green world I want a bread bready world I want a
chocolatey world I want something else I want to do this I want to these are all details
yes these are all details don't see the thing is we have not even as Humanity we
have not even fixed what we really want we are always getting lost in the process isn't it
the problem is the goal is always lost in the process
process is not important where you want to go is important isn't it somebody eats well and
they're happy somebody fast and they're happy somebody does what they want to do and they're
happy somebody doesn't want to do anything and they're happy what's our problem it's okay isn't
so if all of you want the same thing what is the problem
you go when you go home those few people in your house when they are okay when they're up
it's different when they're okay if you gently ask them what do they want they also want the
same thing isn't it they want a peaceful world they want a Joyful World they want a loving world
any man on the street if you stop him when he's walking there as a
human being when he's walking there at the
Indian Pakistani kids different business
when they're just walking as human beings if you ask them what do you want this is what they want
isn't it that man who is right now planting a bomb somewhere what does he want he wants a peaceful
world but he believes it can only happen with a bank yes he is also fighting for that isn't it
if everybody wants the same thing how long should it take
if all of us want the same thing how long should it take it can happen right now isn't it
the problem is yes I want a loving world but if everybody is loving I will also be loving
so if everybody becomes loving you will be the last fool to come
I want to know if everybody becomes loving then you will become loving
is it so do you want to be the last idiot who becomes loving on this planet
is that sure now we are thinking of launching a project to create a loving world
we are starting this from first
October shall we from 1st October
if you want to create a loving world where should it start when should it start it has to start now
from within yourself isn't it there is no other place to start and there is no other time to start
if you truly want to create a loving World it
has to begin here it cannot begin there there there it cannot happen
now creating a loving world what does it mean it does not mean you have to go
on the street screaming to everybody
I love you I love you that's Madness
can you quietly walk on the street and create a loving world
can you work in your office and create a loving world can you cook for just two people at home
and still create a loving world so it does not mean any particular activity whatever
you do you can create a loving World by doing that little action isn't it
now creating a loving world is not service to somebody because
if you are loving your life is Pleasant isn't it now the argument is justice
the problem is this if you're sitting here right now if you make your experience of Life simply
sitting here if you make it very pleasant is that an intelligent way of existence
or you make it unpleasant within yourself is that an intelligent way of existence hmm
being Pleasant so being loving
is an intelligent way of existence or being in anger or hatred is an intelligent way of existence
being loving is an intelligent way to exist now this is not about somebody
this is a sensible way to live for yourself somebody will also benefit that's different
but the most important thing is if you are loving your life has become Pleasant isn't it
love is not about somebody it is the way you are isn't it
love does not mean it's about someone else love is about the way you are if somebody
is here you can share it if nobody is here can you just walk on the street lovingly
yes or no if you're the only person on the planet can you sit here lovingly
yes or no you can isn't it it is your way of being your life has become pleasant but right now
there's a competition if somebody is making a fool of himself right there you want to prove to him I
am not any less than you yes if somebody is not being loving he's just making a fool of himself
an unintelligent way to exist isn't it but right there you want to prove to
that man I am not any less than you
I am much bigger idiot than you are
don't get to this competition this is not about someone else if you are constantly creating a
loving world it is beautiful for you isn't it it will also become beautiful for somebody that's
different you don't even bother about that but it's become beautiful for you isn't it
yes I want to create a loving world but what shall I do I get angry I get jealous
I get this I get that yes those problems are there 24 hours you are not able to exude luck
but every day can you commit yourself that I'll create a loving world
yes every day in the morning whatever time you get up I will not disturb that there will be no drum
okay will not beat the drum for you whatever time you get up when you wake up I want you
to do just one thing first turning when you have a um no just smile and one thought in your mind
today I will create a loving world can you just generate one thought in your head you
run to tell anybody just in your own mind every day the first thought on your mind is
today I will create a loving world can you do this can you do this with a smile on your face
no matter what's happening it doesn't matter what's happened yesterday night it doesn't
matter what you're facing today today you're facing a firing squad still when you wake up
in the morning can you smile and say today I will create a loving world within yourself and get up
just do this one thing because once you commit yourself
for a committed person there is no such thing as failure in his life
there are many lessons to be learned if you fall down 100 times in a day what to do
you'll just says get up and go 100 lessons to be learned that's all but if you are not committed
little if you sleep I told you not possible not possible not possible everywhere you're hearing
this isn't it because you're not committed if you are committed to creating what you care for
oh that is okay but you think it's going to happen have you seen my neighborhood the question is not
whether it's going to happen or not the question is just this do you want to spend your life
creating what you care for or do you want to do some nonsense that you don't care for
is it going to happen who the hell cares whether it happens or not
you are doing what you care for your life becomes beautiful isn't it
if you are creating only what you care for every moment of your life
suppose suppose you get a 15-day vacation what will you do what will you do what will you do
huh
Australia he will go down under
what will you do
huh please he will sleep
what will you do huh
she will read something he will go down and he will sleep she will read somebody will swim
somebody will climb a mountain somebody will go and meet friends somebody will do something else
essentially you will do what you really care for isn't it whatever you care for that's what you do
in your life if you are doing only what you care for your life is one big vacation
see my life is always a vacation you think
I'm working do I look like I'm working you
think I will die of blood pressure I am a die of exhaustion very easily very much possible
but I will not die of blood pressure definitely I will not buy a diet of boredom
that's for sure I am a die of exhaustion many times I'm close
but I will not kill myself out of boredom or blood pressure that will not happen
if you die doing what you enjoy doing is it better than dying of boredom
anyway you will die at least you should have done what you care for isn't it
every moment if you are doing only what you care for your life is one big vacation
then you will not be thinking when to break the work there's no such thing there is no such thing
as taking a break because you're doing what you care for people have something called as work
and vacation if you are committed to creating only what you cared for you only have vacation no work
see I'm just romping around that's
30 years no work busy but no work
it doesn't feel like work it feels like vacation because you're doing
what you care for every moment of your life
now either your activity can become an entanglement or your activity can become
a source of liberation if your activity becomes entanglement we call it karma
if your activity becomes a source of Liberation we call it karma yoga
Karma Yoga does not mean doing extra work
yoga simply means that you're doing what you care for your life is a love affair
your life is a constant love affair with everything that you do
so activity is liberating it is not entangling
it doesn't matter how many hours of work you do per day it's still not entangling
if activity is binding and entangling then it's better you sit at the Temple Gates and beg your
food instead of entangling yourself and entangling everybody around you isn't it see people start off
I you know sometimes I met this girl
this is a lively little girl about 18
20 years of age so exuberant and all
six months later I see her she's become like this
I looked at her and said what happened to you
she said they got me married
I looked at oh this is what marriage does to somebody
if activity is so horribly entangling it is better not do the activity isn't it
have you seen you know I I go back and sometimes
I bump into my old friends to school and college
I am still the same way I remember every bit of what happened and I'm still the same way
they have become accountants doctors engineers
successful
they can't laugh they can't dance they can't do anything anymore because they become successful
they got family they got children and you turn their neck it'll break becomes so stiff
just the activity going to work after all all they have done in their life is just
to earn a goddamn living which every worm can do isn't it yes most people all that they're
doing is just earn a living to earn a living what misery they're causing to themselves
if you come and sit here we will give you two meals every day
you don't have to make yourself if you just sit here joyfully I will
feed you for the rest of your life don't do anything just a happy face
will feed you every day will work no problem just see most human beings on the planet
just to earn a living how tense they become how anxious they've become how horrible they become
if you saw them when they were young children or they were youth they were all yes or no
so if activity is so entangling what is the point doing it
there is really no point doing activity if you are going to entangle yourself and
everybody around you if your activity is liberating you must do a lot of it
if your activity is entangling it's better you don't do anything the world does not need such
activity activity which causes misery is not needed on this planet isn't it
neither for you nor for anybody if it's causing misery what's the point of that activity
so what we've been doing in the last few days is
the slowly people thinking they think they have to go into their grave in installments
no it's not necessary believe me it's not necessary to go into your grave in installments
anyway it'll happen death is super efficient when it happens it's total you have any doubt
you don't have to practice it every day step by step step by step
yes it looks like people are practicing that step by step when they were young
they were like this slowly they're becoming longer longer longer they're practicing
in installments they're becoming dead it is not necessary when it comes it will happen absolutely
you don't have to practice that one thing I'm telling you when it happens
it will happen in a super efficient manner have you ever seen anybody who is halfted
half alive people plenty have you ever seen a half dead man no when they're dead they did isn't it
death death is always a perfect thing please see never happens in an imperfect way isn't it It's
Only Life It's Only Life which can be so imperfect
It's Only Life which can be so incomplete
and if your activity is a process of entanglement then that life is not going to get anywhere
you have to make your activity into process of
Liberation that will only happen if every moment
actively you're creating what you really care for you don't have to create what I care for
if you try to create what I care for you will get blood pressure you must create what you care for
but fortunately if you look deep enough into every human being every human being wants the same thing
on the surface it looks like all of us want different things but if you look deep enough every
human being wants the same thing isn't it so there is really no problem all of us want the same thing
it should happen in a moment but we are waiting for somebody to do it
what you care for must happen out of you isn't it you must have the joy of doing it suppose I
made the whole world loving you didn't have the joy of creating it what a horror it is for you
isn't it I already find the world very very loving Wherever I Go whichever part of the
world it doesn't matter where the moment I land I meet only very loving people always
I get into some Taxi in five minutes that man will be sharing his whole life with me
really the world is already loving you just go you go to one of the
local shops just approach the shopkeeper lovingly will he respond to your lovingly
just stop somebody on the street approach him lovingly will he respond you lovingly
so the world is already loving you are the only one who is missing
if you if you approach anything lovingly it is already loving I'll tell you even the trees
will respond to you lovingly just now we were you know we went to the third Nami Puja in the temple
and it started raining and I said it's fine let it rain and we were going on so somebody one of
our VIP guests who have come they were very concerned how will you do the Arty how will
you do that I didn't say anything I didn't want to say anything one of the brahmacharis said he
was surprised that man is even worried about it he said now when we go to aarti it won't rain
he was looking incredulously the brahmachary is looking at him incredulously how will it
rain when desire when we go out for Earth it will not rain during Earth and we came for
aarti rain stopped we just finished it and it started raining that managed [Applause]
for this man this is incredulous for that boy that is incredulous how can
he even think it'll rain when there is aarti it will not rain
if you are actively creating what you care for everything even a rock will
respond to you in this existence it cannot ignore you even a rock will respond to you
if you are not committed to creating what you care for you get blown around by the
situations in the world either you can live with the joy of creating what you care for
but if it doesn't happen we'll come back again and do it what's the problem
if you're enjoying doing what you're doing if you get one more chance to do it what is the problem
I'm asking yes only if you're suffering your activity you once again I have to do if I if I
give you one you love jamun and you enjoy eating it if I give you one more is it not wonderful
what I've been on then
is it not wonderful
only if you suffer this if I give you a name ball and I give you one more oh you don't like that
one for health I will swallow one more no but if you're enjoying it one more is better isn't it
if you're enjoying the activity that you're doing if you get to do it once again what is the problem
that is no problem isn't it so either you can be in karma or Karma Yoga either activity can
become Liberation or entanglement it is simply in just this simple
process Shifting the context of your life you don't have to change the content of your life
you don't have to do something different you just have to do it differently that's all
you can go to your office wanting to create a loving world today now going to your office is
Like A Love Affair isn't it you are not waiting for a Saturday you are waiting for a Monday
you know in Isha everything is seven days of the week do you know this including the school
he doesn't like it including the school everything is seven days of the week
because I tell them if you're enjoying doing what you're doing
why should there be a holiday if you're not enjoying it please don't be here
if you don't enjoy being here don't be here if you're enjoying it why do you need a break
if you need feels your body needs rest we'll rest some time yes if your body needs rest will rest it
but why do you need a break from what you love to do isn't it if you don't love it don't be here
that's how the world should be the whole world should be like this isn't it if you
don't love being here you must be gone if you love it please be here why do you need a break
looks extreme too
sounds extreme to you
this is all the choice you have either you create what you care for or you suffer your life for the
rest of your life either it's a life sentence or it's a love Faith that's all the choice you have
isn't it either you go through this life like it's a life sentence you've been given a life sentence
or this is a love of faith and you don't have to do something different
you just have to change the context in which you operate